TIM SIMPSON

DATA SCIENTIST

Contact

- 615-971-5160
- https://www.linkedin.com/in/tim-simpson-datasci/
- https://github.com/tjsimpson524/NBA-Rest-Analysis-Project

About

Before data science, I was a free-lance writer, writing daily, everything from articles for a men's fashion blog, to fictional short stories, to screenplays.

My time writing taught me how to extract a story out of the infinite possibilities a blank page, similar to that of an analyst weeding through the noise a dataset to find answers at the heart of a question. I enjoy the search, and know that the skills I honed as a writer -- self-discipline, self-motivation, problem-solving, research, amongst many others -- will translate well to a career as a data scientist.

Projects

NBA Rest Analysis

- Created Shiny app in R using scraped and cleaned NBA gamelog data.
- Broke data down to answer discover the effect of rest on an NBA team.
- View code: https://github.com/tjsimpson524/NBA -Rest-Analysis-Project#nba-restanalysis-project

Education

Nashville Software School

Certificate of Data Science

University of Tennessee in Knoxville

B.A. Speech Communications, 2003

Technical Skills

- Python
- R
- SQL
- Git/Github
- Data Analysis
 - Statistical
 - Modeling
- Webscraping
- Machine Learning

Technical Experience

Data Scientist

Nashville Software School · 2022-2023

Intensive part-time bootcamp focusing on data science fundamentals and problem solving. Used real-world datasets and included projects where findings were presented to stakeholders from the community.

- Wrangled data and performed exploratory data analysis using Python's pandas library and R's tidyverse packages
- Created data visualizations using matplotlib, seaborn, and ggplot2
- Performed geospatial analysis using geopandas and folium
- Gathered data through APIs and webscraping
- Retrieved and analyzed data using PostgreSQL and sqlalchemy
- Built and evaluated statistical and machine learning models using the scikit-learn and statsmodels libraries
- Applied natural language processing using the nltk and spaCy libraries
- Performed network analysis on graph data using Neo4j
- Built and deployed interactive data visualizations using the R Shiny library
- · Source code version control with Git/GitHub
- Project management/tracking with GitHub project boards and issue tracking
- · Interacted with AWS using the CLI and ssh

Professional Experience

Freelance Writer

Los Angeles, CA & Nashville, TN 2010-2021

- Screenwriting
- Fictional short story writing
- Copywriting
- Blog content

Writer's Assistant at Gerolmo Films

Los Angeles, CA 2007-2010

- Collaboration on Academy Nicholl Fellowship semi-finalist project
- Assistant during writing of film and TV series scripts

Master Control Operator

WVLT-TV 8, Knoxville, TN & FOX 17, Nashville 2003-2006

- Monitor all on-air programming
- Work in conjunction with news department on live news casts
- Coordinate with news department on live feeds
- Edit commercial video content for air play
- Troubleshoot issues that arose during live broadcasts and other technical issues